Preliminary Guide to the Julia Penelope Papers, ca. 1986-1999 RL.01010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Julia Penelope papers
ca. 1986-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Penelope, Julia, 1941-
RL.01010
3 Linear Feet
1800 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Also, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Gift, 2000
Biographical Note
Julia Penelope is a feminist and linguist who ran Crossing Press and presently runs Wordwise.
Collection Overview
This accession continues to document Julia Penelope's life as a lesbian and feminist activist and academic. Materials include correspondence and financial records; lecture notes and writings by Penelope dealing with subjects that include linguistics, lesbian communities, lesbian separatists, and coming out; subject files; and book reviews of works by Penelope and others. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture. For information on earlier accessions, please consult the Duke Library online catalog.
Lesbians' writings, American; Feminists -- United States; Lesbians -- United States; Coming out (sexual orientation) -- United States; Lesbian community -- United States; Women -- United States; Linguists-United States; Penelope, Julia, 1941-; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- 2000-0374
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Attention: Correspondence is restricted. Researchers must sign release form agreeing to not reveal personal information.
  - Book reviews, press contracts, subject files, writings, grant proposals, financial materials, and correspondence (Box 1)
    - Book reviews
      - Out of the Class Closet (Box 1)
      - Style (Box 1)
    - Press Contracts
      - "Learning to Live with my Body" (Box 1)
      - "Passing Lesbians" (Box 1)
      - Xword Book (Box 1)
      - Anthology of Penelope's essays (Box 1)
      - For Lesbians Only (Box 1)
      - New Victoria Press (Box 1)
      - Finding the Lesbians (Box 1)
      - International Feminist Fiction (Box 1)
      - Speaking Freely (Box 1)
      - Women and Class Anthology (Box 1)
      - Anthology of Lesbian/Feminist Literary Criticism (Box 1)
      - Lesbian Passages (Box 1)
      - History of Lesbianism (Box 1)
      - Lesbian Culture Anthology (Box 1)
    - Subject Files
      - Milada Marsalka's Memoirs (Box 1)
      - Review Copies Address List (Box 1)
      - Copyright materials (Box 1)
    - Writing
      - "Lesbian Intervention" (Box 1)
    - Grant Proposals
      - NEH Research Grant (Box 1)
      - History of Lesbianism, Book (Box 1)
    - Subject Files
      - Notes, Language and the Gateways of Consciousness (Box 1)
      - Course Materials, Lesbian Novels (Washington University, Fall 1986) (Box 1)
      - Biography of Penelope (Box 1)
      - Materials for Appeal of Non-promotion, University of Nebraska (Box 1)
      - New Found Goddesses (Box 1)
      - Campfest, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Income Tax
      - 1992 (Box 1)
      - 1993 (Box 1)
      - 1994 (Box 1)
    - Appointment Book 1994 (Box 1)
    - Letters and Cards, 1993-1994
      - Lesbian Culture (Box 1)
      - Carytis Cardea (Box 1)
    - Loose Material
      - Miscellaneous photocopies from books and magazines (Box 1)
    - Notecards on Contributors to Out of the Class Closet (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Attention: May be restricted: If correspondence, then users must sign release form.
    - Sojourner, 1996 January (Box 1)
    - Grade Book, University of Massachusetts, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Picture, Two Young Women Reading a Book Together (Box 1)
  - Subject files, writings, correspondence, book reviews, and feminist crossword puzzle book (Box 2)
    Attention: Remove rusty fasteners.
    - Subject files
      - Hol 1: Antiquity (Box 2)
      - Kamasutra of Vaysayana (Box 2)
      - Near East Archeology (Box 2)
      - International Feminist Fiction Anthology (First Choice Stories) (Box 2)
      - [Verbal Self Defense] (Box 2)
      - Lesbian Language (Box 2)
      - Consent to Publish Agreements (Box 2)
      - Request for Permission to Reprint (Box 2)
      - Bookstores and Addresses (U.S) (Box 2)
      - Carol Barret's poem (Box 2)
      - Skanking (Box 2)
      - Homosexuality and Citizenship in Florida (Box 2)
      - Johnson, Linnea, Analysis of Rosenwasser Letter (Box 2)
      - Sexual Practice/Textual Theory, Letter File (Box 2)
      - Class Discussion (Box 2)
      - My Horoscope (Box 2)
      - Dream and Disappointment (Box 2)
      - Marcia Gagliardi, Poems (Box 2)
      - Review Copies, Address List (Box 2)
      - Article on St. Louis, Notes (Box 2)
      - SEPS (Box 2)
      - Naiad Press Incorporation Papers (Box 2)
      - WomaNews Response (Box 2)
      - List of Lesbian Myths (Box 2)
      - Morgan Grey, "Purple Dragon Song" (Box 2)
      - Book on Lesbian Etiquette (Box 2)
      - Crossing Promo Flyers (Box 2)
      - SEP Workshop, Michigan '89 (Box 2)
      - The Sexist Tradition: Words and Meaning (Box 2)
    - Speaking Freely: Teachers College Press Reprint (1992)
      - 1998 Poetry Book (Box 2)
      - Blackwell, Hobby and White Proposal (Box 2)
      - Julia at Mountain Moving Coffee House (Box 2)
      - [Unidentified Manuscript] (Box 2)
    - Writings
      - On the Creation of Errors in Student Writing, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - "Dyke Arrogance: Self-Righteousness, Trashing, and Cheap Thrills" (Box 2)
      - My Life, A Cartesian Model (Box 2)
      - "Language and Women's Oppression" (Box 2)
      - UPTIME Interview (Box 2)
      - Letter to Newspapers: Kate and Julia (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      Attention: Restricted. Users must sign release form.
      - Letters to be Answered, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Gearhart Correspondence (1989) (Box 2)
      - Personal Papers Correspondence and Contents Lists (Box 2)
    - Book Reviews
      - You Just Don't Understand, D. Tannen (Box 2)
      - Lesbian Culture (Box 2)
      - Sexual Practice/Textual Theory (Box 2)
    - Feminist Crossword Puzzle Book (Box 2)